Harry Hoijer Collection 1930-1976 Mss.497.3.H68
American Philosophical Society
- Series II. Works by Hoijer (Box 1)
  - Mescalero fieldnotes, n.d.; 4503, 4504; 5 notebooks; Hoijer, Harry, 1904-1976 (Box 3)
    - Mescalero Apache Texts, notebook 5, 1934; 4504; Hoijer, Harry, 1904-1976 (Box 3)
      Frog and Coyote (pp. 6-44) [possibly this text continues in another notebook]
  - Navajo Lexicon, n.d.; 4565; ca. 450p.; Hoijer, Harry, 1904-1976 (Volume 1)
    Assorted lexical material, arranged in groups, including theme prefixes, stems, particles, enclitics, etc. According to Kendall, this is the manuscript of a lexicon published in the University of California Publications in Linguistics series (no. 78, 1974). Lexical items are numbered; pages are mostly unnumbered.
  - Navajo Night Chant, Feb. 25-Mar. 8, 1930-1932; 4566; 5 notebooks; Hoijer, Harry, 1904-1976 (Box 4)
    All vols. labeled "Harry Hoijer, Navaho Night Chant," numbered consecutively, vols. I-V. Chant is written down in phonemic transcription, with additional notes in English on language and ceremony. References to cylinders [recordings]. Additional notes in the front pages of notebook 1 indicate that these are songs of Navaho Night Chant, started Feb. 25, 1930. Kechi-informant Frank Gould--interpreter". Reverse of page reads: "The first 75 not recorded by me--previously done by A. J. [?] Newcomb".
    According to a letter from Dorothy Hoijer [see correspondence], this was done in collaboration with Edward Sapir.
    Diagrams in vols. II and IV. Note at the end of vol. V: "Written up April 3, 1932".
  - Navajo Songs, 1930-1932; 4567; 11 notebooks (ca.60p. each); Hoijer, Harry, 1904-1976 (Box 4)
    Numbered consecutively, labeled "Harry Hoijer, Navaho Songs". Songs are written in phonemic transcription, with interlinear glosses and English translations. Some notes on ceremonial conduct. Internal reference to cylinders [recordings]. Navajo titles are listed on the first page of each notebook.
    - Navajo songs, Notebook 1, 1931; Hoijer, Harry, 1904-1976 (Box 4)
      "Translated: ready to type, written up Oct. 9, 1931"
      Two Twins (Song #1)
      Red Ants (#2)
      Coming of the Water (#3)
      Wolf (#4)
      Locusts (#5)
      Emergence (#6)
      There are No Men (#7)
      Coyote Steals Fire (#8)
      Locust (#9)
      Sweathouse (#10)
    - Navajo songs, Notebook 2, 1930; Hoijer, Harry, 1904-1976 (Box 4)
      Hogan (#11)
      Mountain (#12)
      Sun (#13)
      World Spirit (#14)
      Salt Woman Song (#15)
      Making the Stars (#16)
      They Saw Each Other (#17)
    - Navajo songs, Notebook 3, 1932; Hoijer, Harry, 1904-1976 (Box 4)
      "Finished Feb. 18, 1932"
      Changing Woman is Born (#18)
      Changing Woman is Washed (#19)
      Corn Song (#20)
      Changing Woman East (#21)
      Changing Woman Puberty Ceremony Song (#22-23)
      Changing Woman is Dressed (#24)
      Changing Woman Praised (#25)
      First Menstruation (#26)
    - Navajo songs, Notebook 4, 1932; Hoijer, Harry, 1904-1976 (Box 4)
      "Finished Feb. 22 [1932]"
      Pray for birth (#27)
      Impregnation (#28)
      Birth (#29)
      Afterbirth (#30)
      Cutting of cord (#31)
      Washing of babies (#32)
      The babies eat (#33)
      [songs 34 - 50: Visit to the Sun]
      Boys are to leave home (#34)
      Their visit to their Father, the Sun (#35-38)
      The boys go over the sacred mountains (#39)
      Other obstacles (#40)
      Through the darknesses (#41)
      They great the darknesses (#42)
      Greeting the dawn (#43) [continued in Vol. V]
    - Navajo songs, Notebook 5, 1930; Hoijer, Harry, 1904-1976 (Box 4)
      Greeting the dawn (#43) [continued from Vol. IV]
      Pass through old age demons (#44-47)
      Spider song (#48)
      Caterpillar song (#49)
      Cross the ocean (#50)
      [songs 51-63: Tests and acceptance at Sun's house]
      Arrival at Sun's house (#51)
      Tests by the Sun (#52-53)
      Tobacco Song (#54)
      Sun clothes them (#55)
      Sun feeds them (#56)
      Sun talks with them (#57)
      They work together (#58)
      Kills the Talking Giant (#59-63)
    - Navajo songs, Notebook 6, March 5, 1932; Hoijer, Harry, 1904-1976 (Box 4)
      [Boy's adventures]
      Wind song (#64)
      Ssongs 65-82 [no titles]
    - Navajo songs, Notebook 7, 1930; Hoijer, Harry, 1904-1976 (Box 4)
      Election of First Chief (#83-90)
      Creation of men as things of our present earth (#91-99)
    - Navajo songs, Notebook 8, 1930; Hoijer, Harry, 1904-1976 (Box 5)
      Earth song (#100-101)
      Mountain song (#102-103)
      Dawn songs (#104)
      Changing Woman's journey to Santa Cruz (#105-106)
      Bear song (#107-112)
      Hogan song (#113)
      Gods come to hogan to welcome children (#114)
      Children arrive at hogan (#115-116) [continued in Vol. IX]
    - Navajo songs, Notebook 9, 1930; Hoijer, Harry, 1904-1976 (Box 5)
      Children arrive at hogan (#117-118)
      Changing Woman's prayer stick (#119-120)
      He who comes with dawn = Talking God's song (#121-122)
      Corn Pollen Boy's song (#123-124)
      Talking God's song (#125-132) [continued in Vol. X]
    - Navajo songs, Notebook 10, 1930; Hoijer, Harry, 1904-1976 (Box 5)
      Talking God's song (#133-135)
      Sun Song (#136)
      Food Song (#137)
      Tobacco Song (#138-139)
      Song of Mountain's Little Ones (#140-143)
      Children's song (#144-152) [continued in Vol. XI]
    - Navajo songs, Notebook 11, 1930; Hoijer, Harry, 1904-1976 (Box 5)
      Children's song (#152-153)
      [one of the principal gods] (#154-158)
      Rainbow song (#159)
      Changing Woman's song (#160)
      Children answer questions of Changing Woman (#161)
      Blue Horse Song (#162)
      Corn Song (#163-164)
      Corn Bug Boy song (#165)
      Dawn song (#166-169)
  - Navajo Texts with translations, November 21, December 12, 1956; 4570; 32p.; Hoijer, Harry, 1904-1976 (Box 5, Box 1)
    Two untitled texts. Handwritten looseleaf pages, in phonemic transcription with interlinear English glosses, taken from a recording [not included in collection?].
    (1) Informant: Ralph Roanhorse. Nov. 21, 1956. Begins: "When I was still a small child..." (17 pp.)
    (2) Informant: Ralph Roanhorse. Dec. 12, 1956. Begins: "This coyote, the bolting one..." (15 pp.)
  - San Carlos texts, n.d.; 4704; 325p.; Hoijer, Harry, 1904-1976 (Box 5, Box 1)
    Note inside reads "San Carlos or Chiricahua?"
    Texts in phonemic transcription: (a) with handwritten corrections, (b) in corrected copy, with carbon copy of same [no English glosses or translations]; each section numbered separately.
    - San Carlos texts, n.d.; Hoijer, Harry, 1904-1976 (Box 5, Folder 1)
      Coyote and Fox (6 pp)
      The Apache and the Mountain Lions (7 pp)
      The Deer Hunters (7 pp)
      A Misadventure with a Horse (4 pp)
      An Adventure with a Bull (10 pp)
      The Apache Sweethearts (6 pp)
      The Boy and His Sweetheart (4 pp)
      Migrations of an Apache Clan (3 pp)
      An Apache Raid on the Pima (7 pp)
    - San Carlos texts, n.d.; Hoijer, Harry, 1904-1976 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      First Contacts with the Whites (14 pp)
      A Pima Raid on the Apache (10 pp)
      Old Time Food and Clothing (9 pp)
      An Apache's Advice to His Children (7 pp)
      Apache Courtship (13 pp)
      First Experiences with American Food (14 pp)
    - San Carlos texts, Hoijer, Harry, 1904-1976 (Box 5, Folder 3)
      The Story of Killer of Enemies (pp. 1-89)
    - San Carlos texts, n.d.; Hoijer, Harry, 1904-1976 (Box 5, Folder 4)
      The Story of Killer of Enemies (pp. 1-57 and carbon copy)
  - Sarsi slip file, n.d.; 4705; [all verbal data]; Hoijer, Harry, 1904-1976 (Othertype Slipfile 2)
    3x5 typed index cards illustrating postpositions; 5x7 handwritten slips with examples of verbal data, including negation, progressives, iteratives, etc. Acc. to Kendall, these were taken from Sapir's notebooks.
- Series III. Works Collected by Hoijer (Box 6)
  - Goddard's Jicarilla Texts, rewritten, n.d.; 4429; 1 notebook; Haile, Berard, 1874-1961 (Box 6)
    One notebook, labeled "Goddard's re-written 1-40. Jicarilla". Inside front cover reads: "Jicarilla Texts. Goddard's #22 pp. 1-27; #80 cont. 28--." Text is contained on numbered pages 1-40 (notebook was first numbered pp. 661-720). Recorded by Pliny Earle Goddard.
  - Jicarilla Fieldnotes, n.d.; 4427; 5 notebooks; Haile, Berard, 1874-1961 (Box 6)
    "Jicarilla Texts, tr. Berard Haile, O.F.M.", numbered consecutively, pp. 1-292. Jicarilla texts in phonemic transcription, with interlinear English glosses on right-hand pages. Left-hand pages contain notes on the text. Some are untitled. No indication of place, date, or informant. [Handwritten note says these are not the same texts as in Kendall 4426].
    - Jicarilla texts: Notebook 1. The Dwelling Place of the People under the Earth (pp. 17-60), pp.1-60; Haile, Berard, 1874-1961 (Box 6)
    - Jicarilla texts: Notebook 2, n.d.; pp.61-120; Haile, Berard, 1874-1961 (Box 6)
      Monster Fish (pp. 70-110)
      Owl Monster (pp. 111-114)
      Snapping Rock (pp. 115-116)
      Big Toad Monster (p. 117)
      The Two Running Rocks (pp. 118-120)
    - Jicarilla texts: Notebook 3 [no sub titles provided], n.d.; pp.121-180; Haile, Berard, 1874-1961 (Box 6)
    - Jicarilla texts: Notebook 4 [The Monster Toad (pp. 193-240)], pp.181-240; Haile, Berard, 1874-1961 (Box 6)
    - Jicarilla texts: Notebook 5 [Masked Dance (pp. 242-292)], pp.241-292; Haile, Berard, 1874-1961 (Box 6)
  - Jicarilla Texts in Translation, n.d.; 4428; 3 notebooks; Haile, Berard, 1874-1961 (Box 6)
    Translations of Jicarilla texts and detailed additional notes on the matter of the texts, with references throughout to "H.V." and "J.J.V.". The three notebooks are numbered consecutively, pp. 17-242. The pages (now loose) were written on one side only. According to Kendall, the numbers on each notebook correspond to notebooks of Jicarilla texts [see Box 2]. No indication of place, date, or informant. Only the first title is supplied.
    - Notebook 1, n.d.; pp. 17-78; Haile, Berard, 1874-1961 (Box 6)
    - Notebook 2, n.d.; pp. 78-166; Haile, Berard, 1874-1961 (Box 6)
    - Notebook 3, n.d.; pp. 116-242; Haile, Berard, 1874-1961 (Box 6)
  - Jicarilla Texts, n.d.; 4426; ca.304p.; Haile, Berard, 1874-1961 (Box 6)
    Typed ms, containing Jicarilla texts in phonemic transcription, with an interlinear English gloss. Typed footnotes add primarily linguistic commentary. Handwritten corrections to both Jicarilla and English. Handwritten English translations on separately numbered pages. No indication of place, date, or informant. Approximately 250 pp of typed text and 54 pp of handwritten translations. Much of the manuscript is written on the back of typed pages.
    - Jicarilla Texts: The Emergence from the Underworld, Haile, Berard, 1874-1961 (Box 6)
      Text, pp. 1-36.
    - Jicarilla Texts: The Emergence from the Underworld (translation), 15p.; Haile, Berard, 1874-1961 (Box 6)
    - Jicarilla Texts: The Destruction of the Monsters, Haile, Berard, 1874-1961 (Box 6)
      Text, pp. 37-92.
    - Jicarilla Texts: The Destruction of the Monsters (translation), 6p.; Haile, Berard, 1874-1961 (Box 6)
    - Jicarilla Texts: The Killing of the Fat-Headed Monsters, Haile, Berard, 1874-1961 (Box 6)
      Text, pp. 93-105.
    - Jicarilla Texts: The Killing of the Fat-Headed Monsters (translation), 6p.; Haile, Berard, 1874-1961 (Box 6)
    - Jicarilla Texts: The há.ct'cin Create Man, Haile, Berard, 1874-1961 (Box 6)
      Text, pp. 160a-121.
    - Jicarilla Texts: The há.ct'cin Create Man (translation), 6p.; Haile, Berard, 1874-1961 (Box 6)
    - Jicarilla Texts: Killer of Enemies and the Eagles, Haile, Berard, 1874-1961 (Box 6)
      Text, pp. 121a-145.
    - Jicarilla Texts: Killer of Enemies and the Eagles (translation), 9p.; Haile, Berard, 1874-1961 (Box 6)
    - Jicarilla Texts: Killer of Enemies and the WaterMonster, Haile, Berard, 1874-1961 (Box 6)
      Text, pp. 145a-243.
  - Sarsi text and notes, 1937?; 4706; 1 notebook; Jenness, Diamond, 1886-1969 (Box 7)
    Transcribed words and phrases, in the fashion of a compiled lexicon (pp. 1-27). "Story of Thunder and Crow, dictated by John Whitney"--text with interlinear English gloss (pp. 28-29). Parsed verbs: 'I am sitting on it, you are???, he is???', etc. (pp. 29-31)
  - San Carlos Apache Texts, August 1933; 4703; 25p.; Mandelbaum, David (Box 7)
    Handwritten pages in phonemic transcription, with interlinear English glosses. P. 1 reads: "Texts--San Carlos Apache. Informant--Lewis Russell. Taken August 1933. D. G. Mandelbaum."
    Holy Ground Prayer
    Silas John Symbols
    Daily Prayer
    Profession of Faith
    To Learn Apache
    Prayers and Symbols
    Silas John's Revelation
    The Apache Kid
  - Navajo texts, 1937-1938; 4572; 5 folders; Sandoval, Chic (Box 7)
    Cover sheet reads "Navajo Texts recorded by Chick [sic] Sandoval". Handwritten pages of Navajo texts in phonemic transcription, with interlinear glosses in English, followed by English translations. Annotated with dates, indicating date received [in hand of E. Sapir?]. Approx. 200 pp. [see also, correspondence, Kendall 4572]
    - Navajo texts, April-June 1937; Sandoval, Chic (Folder 1)
      Letter from H. J. Ostrander to Univ. of Chicago, Apr. 10, 1939
      Letter from H. J. Ostrander to E. G. Conklin, Apr. 10, 1939
      Letter from Frederick Woodward to H. J. Ostrander, Apr. 14, 1939
      Letter from Chic Sandoval to Harry Hoijer, Apr. 21, 1939
      Letter of April 20, 1937, A. G. Sandoval [written on both sides of page] (3 pp.). Includes children's story of Tur key and giant
      Yellow Fox (pp. 1-16 and 17-25) [June 3, 1937]
      Coyote and Skunk (pp.26-34 and 35-39) [June 29, 1937]
    - Navajo texts, October 18, 1937; Sandoval, Chic (Folder 2)
      Coyote and Cotton-Tailed Rabbit (pp. 40-44 and 45-47)
      Coyote and Deer (pp. 48-53; no English translation)
      Coyote and Gray Lizard (pp. 54-56; no transcription)
      Coyote and Porcupine (pp. 57-66 and 67-73)
      Cripples Their Sayings [sic] (pp. 74-76 and 77-79)
    - Navajo texts, January 8, 1938; Sandoval, Chic (Folder 3)
      pp. 80-104 contain phonemic transcriptions with English glosses
      Coyote and the Beaver People (pp. 80-82)
      Coyote and Porcupine (pp. 83-84)
      Coyote and Swallows (pp. 85-87)
      Coyote and Horned Toad (pp. 87-92)
      Coyote and Prairie Dog (pp. 93-94)
      Coyote and Badger (pp. 95-97)
      Coyote and Wild Cat (pp. 98-104)
      English translations (pp. 105-119)
    - Navajo texts, March 5, 1938; Sandoval, Chic (Folder 4)
      Maiden Who Turned into Bear (pp. 120-148, phonemic transcription with English gloss; pp. 149-164, English translation)
    - Navajo texts, June 1, 1938; Sandoval, Chic (Folder 5)
      Concerning One Who Was Reared by Old Man Owl and Old Lady Owl (pp. 165-181, phonemic transcription with English gloss; pp. 182-191, English translation)
      Admonition ("Get up! Get up!") and separately numbered (5 pages of transcription, 5 pages of translation)
  - Navajo conversations, n.d.; 4569; Sapir, Edward, 1884-1939 (Box 7)
    Two conversations, handwritten on 3x5 slips, 7 slips total. No indications of date, place, or informant. According to Kendall, conversations and English translations, in Sapir's hand, with additions by Hoijer.
  - Tales of the Sarcee Indians, 1966; 4708; 10 folders; Sapir, Edward, 1884-1939 (Box 7)
    Folder 1-4 contain typed mss of Sarci tales in phonemic transcription, one or more copies of the typescript, with English glosses written in Sapir's hand. Folders #5-10 contain only the typed transcription, no English glosses; tales are not always numbered.
    - Tales of the Sarcee Indians, 1966; Sapir, Edward, 1884-1939 (Folder 1)
      Includes handwritten table of contents (1 page). Inserted note reads: "original typed texts and trans[lations] sent to [Victor] Golla, Nov. 15, 1966". How Spotted-Eagle and Crow-Flag Brought Home the Medicine-Pipe (pp. 8, 7) no. 1.
    - Tales of the Sarcee Indians, 1966; Sapir, Edward, 1884-1939 (Folder 2)
      The Origin of the Beaver Bundle (pp. 2, 2) no. 2
      The Origin of the Ghost Dance (pp. 7, 6) no. 4
    - Tales of the Sarcee Indians, 1966; Sapir, Edward, 1884-1939 (Folder 3)
      How the Sarcee Were Split Up (pp. 1, 1) no. 3
      Buffalo Lake (pp. 1, 1)
      The Girl Who Married a Star (pp. 5, 4)
    - Tales of the Sarcee Indians, 1966; Sapir, Edward, 1884-1939 (Folder 4)
      The Man Who Chopped a Log into the River with His Brother (pp. 4, 8)
    - Tales of the Sarcee Indians, 1966; Sapir, Edward, 1884-1939 (Folder 5)
      The Origin of the Dipper (5pp.)
      Raised-by-his-grandmother (8pp.)
    - Tales of the Sarcee Indians, 1966; Sapir, Edward, 1884-1939 (Folder 6)
      How He Starved His Father-in-law (5pp.)
      The Woman Who Married a Dog (3pp.)
      Lodge-boy and Thrown-away (7pp.)
    - Tales of the Sarcee Indians, 1966; Sapir, Edward, 1884-1939 (Folder 7)
      Thunder Bird and Crow (1p.) no. 13
      Old Man (in three parts; 13 pp total) no. 14
    - Tales of the Sarcee Indians, 1966; Sapir, Edward, 1884-1939 (Folder 8)
      The Wicked Medicine Man (4pp.)
      How the Pipe Bundle Was Transferred to Chief Big-Belly (2pp.)
      The Time the Sarcees Killed Some Gros Ventre (3pp.)
      Young Bull and Lizard (3pp.)
    - Tales of the Sarcee Indians, 1966; Sapir, Edward, 1884-1939 (Folder 9)
      The Man That Was Sacrificed (5pp.)
      The Girl Who Refused to Live (2pp.)
      Piegan-boy Is Shot (3pp.)
      Chef Bull-Head Kills His Son by Mistake (3pp.)
    - Tales of the Sarcee Indians, 1966; Sapir, Edward, 1884-1939 (Folder 10)
      Little-Chief Is Killed by the Cree (2pp.)
      The Battle at Cut-Knife Creek (2pp.)
      Beaver-Collar Steps into the Enemy's Tent (2pp.)
      Little-Bear's Vision (2pp.)
  - Navajo grammatical notes, Late 1920s; 4575; ca. 90 5x7 handwritten slips; Sapir, Edward and Harry Hoijer (Box 7)
    Inserted note reads "both Sapir and Hoijer, prob. from the late 1920s, when Hoijer was a graduate student (DLK)". Acc. to Kendall, notes on various aspects of Navajo grammar and phonetics, some comparison with other Athapascan languages, some reconstruction of Proto-A. II.
- Series IV. Audio Recordings (Box 1)
  Loucheux words and brief phrases given in response to English.
  - Loucheux (Kuchin) recordings, July 29-30, 1964; 4 reels; Hoijer, Harry, 1904-1976 (Box 1)